Sierra Club, Atlantic Chapter; Records apap130
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Sierra Club, Atlantic Chapter Records
1964-1999
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap130
29 cubic ft. 9 videotapes, 1 film reel, 1 audiotape
The collection documents the day-to-day work of the Sierra Club's Atlantic Chapter over three and a half decades.
Administrative History
The Sierra Club (http://www.sierraclub.org) is a national environmental organization founded in California in 1892 by naturalist and explorer John Muir with the mission to "explore, enjoy and protect the wild places of the earth" [Sierra Club. Accessed May 11, 2005 [http://www.sierraclub.org]. The Atlantic Chapter is responsible for the Sierra Club's membership and activities in New York, and deals with a variety of environmental issues in the state, such as land use controls, pollution, recycling, and endangered species and habitat protection. First formed in 1950, the Atlantic Chapter originally spanned the entire eastern seaboard, but several new state organizations were formed in the 1960s and early 1970s, and from 1972 on, the name "Atlantic Chapter" was restricted to just New York [Information on the early Atlantic Chapter is found in S. Ogilvy and J. Nunn, "Sierra Club expansion and evolution: The Atlantic Chapter, 1957-1969", in Sierra Club History Committee, The Sierra Club Nationwide: Interviews. San Francisco, CA: Sierra Club History Committee, 1983]. Further information about the Sierra Club Atlantic Chapter can be found at http://newyork.sierraclub.org. This collection contains the records of the Atlantic Chapter from the mid-1960s through the 1990s.
The Atlantic Chapter, headquartered in Albany since 1978, has devoted much of its energy to battling what it regards as environmentally unsound development projects, and to cleaning up or eliminating pollution. In the late 1960s and 1970s the chapter fought the proposed nuclear power plant at Storm King Mountain on the Hudson River and the proposed Westway Highway in Manhattan, was involved in the exposure of the toxic contamination at Love Canal, raised concerns about construction at the Lake Placid Olympic site, and issued warnings about PCBs in the Hudson River and acid rain. The 1980s was a mixed decade for the Chapter. It racked up a number of successes, such as taking part in the petition drive to remove James Watt as U.S. Secretary of the Interior, lobbying for beverage container recycling, supporting the election of Mario Cuomo as New York governor (though later disagreeing with him on a number of issues), fighting to protect the Lake Minnewaska/Shawangunk Mountains area, and successfully campaigning for passage of the Environmental Quality Bond Act of 1986. But the Chapter also suffered financial and ethical problems. Expenses early in the decade far exceeded income, resulting in a debt of $60,000 by 1983, which forced the national organization to put the Chapter into trusteeship in 1987. The Atlantic Chapter was also plagued by infighting, accusations of rigged elections, and the embarrassing discovery that the Chapter's delegate to the Sierra Club Council, Walter Blank, had been illegally dumping toxic chemicals from his pest control business. The Chapter recovered in the 1990s and undertook some of its most intense activity ever, pushing for passage of the unsuccessful Environmental Quality Bond Act of 1990, urging environmentally sound land use policies in the Adirondack Park, and taking part in the widespread opposition to the James Bay hydroelectric project. The Chapter opposed the candidacy of George Pataki for New York governor, but later developed an uneasy working relationship with him after his election. The Chapter supported Pataki on some issues, while opposing him on a number of other initiatives such as regulatory reform and budget and personnel cuts at the Department of Environmental Conservation.
Based upon chapter directories from 1988-1993, the Atlantic Chapter in the early 1990s was structured as follows. The statewide organization was headed by four officers: the chair, vice-chair, secretary, and treasurer. Chairs of the Atlantic Chapter have included Alfred Forsyth (?-1972), Ted Hullar (1972-?), Irven Rinard (?-1978), Samuel Sage (1978-1984), Pam Woywood (1984-1986), Al Hauser (1986-1987?), Jim Carr (1987-1988), Rich Fedele (1988-1991), Don Young (1991-?), and Ken Baer (?-Present). There was also a Board of Governance consisting of twenty-seven members, eighteen of whom represented particular regional groups, while nine were at-large members. Nine members of the Board of Governance made up the Executive Committee. Four people served as delegates to larger Sierra Club bodies: three to the (Northeast) Regional Conservation Committee, and one to the Sierra Club Council. The state organization further consisted of administrative committees and conservation committees. The eighteen administrative committees handled the various operational concerns of the chapter. These committees were: Archives, By-laws, Compliance Officer, Computer, Consumer Education, Elections, Environmental Education, Financial Affairs, Fundraising, Honors and Awards, Legal, Newsletter Editor, Nominating, Office and Personnel, Outings, Political, Publications Rep, and Training Coordinator. The sixteen conservation committees dealt with specific environmental issues at the state level. These committees were: Adirondacks, Catskills, Energy, Great Lakes, Industrial Pre-Treatment, International, James Bay Defense, Ozone, Pesticides, Population, Public Lands, Solid Waste, Toxics/Radioactive Waste, Transportation, Water Resources, and Wildlife/Wilderness, plus a Conservation Chair and Vice-Chair.
The Atlantic Chapter divided New York State into eleven regional groups, which dealt with local environmental issues, possessed their own internal organization, issued their own newsletters, and sent representatives to the state Board of Governance. The regional groups in 1993 were: Finger Lakes, Hudson-Mohawk, Iroquois, Long Island, Lower Hudson (aka Westchester/Putnam), Mid-Hudson, New York City, Niagara, Ramapo-Catskill, Rochester, and Susquehanna.
The Sierra Club Atlantic Chapter, as of 2005, consists of three paid staff members-the chapter legislative director, the chapter legislative associate, and the chapter coordinator-and the volunteer leaders, of which there are five officers (chair, vice-chair, secretary, treasurer, and conservation chair) and twenty-four conservation issue chairs. The chairs cover the following issues: Air Quality, Airports, Adirondacks, Biodiversity/Earth Diet, Energy, Environmental Education, Environmental Justice, Farm and Food, Global Warming, Great Lakes, International Population, Legislative, Open Space, Shawangunks, Sprawl, Sterling Forest/Highlands, St. Lawrence Cement Plant Task Force, Superfund/Brownfields, Sustainable Forestry, Solid Waste, Toxic Waste, Wetlands, Wildlife and Wilderness. The Sierra Club Atlantic Chapter currently possesses a membership of about 40,000.
Scope and Contents
The collection documents the work of the Atlantic Chapter over three and a half decades. The earliest item is from 1964, but continuous records begin in 1967 and run up to 1999, with the large bulk of the materials dating from the 1980s and 1990s.
Topics that are extensively documented in the collection include: the Storm King Mountain controversy, the Westway Hghway, low-level radioactive waste, land use in the Adirondack Park, New York State compliance with the Clean Air Act, the Clean Water/Clean Air Bond Act of 1996, the electric industry in New York State, environmental attitudes of New York State politicians, the recycling of beverage containers, the use of sludge in agriculture, Long Island drinking water contamination by pesticides, the James Bay controversy, financial problems in the 1980s, and wildlife and habitat preservation. The collection also contains records from the national Sierra Club organization, and documents from other environmental organizations such as the Citizens' Environmental Coalition, the Environmental Planning Lobby, Hudsonia, the League of Conservation Voters, the National Audubon Society, the New York State Public Interest Research Group (NYPIRG), and Scenic Hudson.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is arranged into eight series.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by the Sierra Club, Atlantic Chapterin April 2002. An accession of .4 cubic ft. was received in February 2004 from the Bancroft Library, UC Berkeley, which is the official repository of the Sierra Club. The department recieved additional records from Deborah West Zipf in 2012, Caitlin Ferrante in 2017, and Roger Gray in 2025.
Related Materials
The Sierra Atlantic newsletter from Spring 2003 to the present is available online at http://newyork.sierraclub.org/Sierra%20Atlantic/index.htm. The records of the national Sierra Club are housed at the Bancroft Library of the University of California-Berkeley, and their finding aid can be accessed online at http://www.oac.cdlib.org/findaid/ark:/13030/tf4x0nb0qs.
Several collections in the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives provide further information on the environmental issues that were of concern to the Sierra Club, Atlantic Chapter. A complete list of collections is available at the subject guide for Conservation and the Environment. Of particular note are the records of Environmental Advocates of New York Records (APAP-104), Nancy Papish Papers (APAP-144), and the Solidarity Committee of the Capital District Records (APAP-042), which include files related to the campaign to stop Hydro-Quebec's James Bay II project.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Social Activists and Public Advocates; Native Americans; Conservation and the Environment; Air quality--New York (State).; Ecology--New York (State).; Environmentalism--New York (State).; Hazardous wastes--New York (State).; Pesticides--New York (State).; Water quality--New York (State).; Minutes (administrative records); Budgets; By-laws (administrative records); Clippings; Files by subject; Correspondence; Newsletters; Videocassettes; Sierra Club; Sierra Club--Atlantic Chapter; James Bay Hydroelectric Project
- Administrative Files, 1967-1997; 1; 2.3 cubic ft.
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of materials relating directly to the operations of the Atlantic Chapter. There is one folder of items covering the late 1960s through the 1970s (General Records, 1967-1979), but most of the series dates from the 1980s and 1990s. The records of important chapter bodies such as eight of the eighteen administrative committees, the Board of Governance, and the Executive Committee are included here, and there are lists of chapter members and officers. Other items found in the series include budget materials, by-laws, fundraising letters, general correspondence, and invoices.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Administrative Assistant, 1998 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 1)
  - Administrative Committees, Elections Committee, 1986-1988 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 2)
  - Administrative Committees, Financial Affairs Committee, 1988-1989 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 3)
  - Administrative Committees, Financial Affairs Committee, 1988-1989 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 4)
  - Administrative Committees, Group Size Committee, 1987-1988 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 5)
  - Administrative Committees, Legal Committee, 1988-1989 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 6)
  - Administrative Committees, Nominating Committee, 1988-1989 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 7)
  - Administrative Committees, Outings Committee, 1987-1988 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 8)
  - Administrative Committees, Outings Committee, 1987; 1988 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 9)
  - Administrative Committees, Political Committee, 1991 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 10)
  - Administrative Committees, Political Committee, 1994 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 11)
  - Administrative Committees, Publications Committee, 1989-1991 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 12)
  - Albany Office, 1991-1992 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 13)
  - Areas of Responsibility for the Chapters, 1987 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 14)
  - Board of Governance, Meeting Cost Project, ca. 1993 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 15)
  - Board of Governance, Meetings, 1982 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 16)
  - Board of Governance, Meetings, 1983 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 17)
  - Board of Governance, Meetings, 1984 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 18)
  - Board of Governance, Meetings, 1984-1987 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 19)
  - Board of Governance, Meetings, 1985 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 20)
  - Board of Governance, Meetings, 1985 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 21)
  - Board of Governance, Meetings, 1987 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 22)
  - Board of Governance, Meetings, 1988 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 23)
  - Board of Governance, Meetings, 1989 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 24)
  - Board of Governance, Meetings, 1990 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 25)
  - Board of Governance, Meetings, 1990 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 26)
  - Board of Governance, Meetings, 1991 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 27)
  - Board of Governance, Meetings, 1992 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 28)
  - Board of Governance, Meetings, 1993 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 29)
  - Board of Governance, Meetings, 1994-1995 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 30)
  - Board of Governance, Meetings, 1994-1998 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 31)
  - Board of Governance, Meetings, 1994-1998 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 32)
  - Board of Governance, Members, 1989 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 33)
  - Board of Governance, Members Policy, 1988 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 34)
  - Board of Governance, Notices, 1994 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 35)
  - Board of Governance, Reorganization, 1990 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 36)
  - Board of Governance, Resolutions, 1982-1987 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 37)
  - Board of Governance, Resolutions, 1982-1987 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 38)
  - Budgets, 1986-1989 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 39)
  - Budgets, 1993-1995 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 40)
  - Burnout Prevention, 1992 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 41)
  - By-laws, ca. 1991 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 42)
  - By-laws, 1982-1991 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 43)
  - Certificate of Appreciation to Atlantic Chapter, 1990 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 44)
  - Chapter, Board of Governance, Executive Committee. Meeting Dates, 1989 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 45)
  - Chapter Operations Manual, 1977 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 46)
  - Chapter Organization, 1994 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 47)
  - Conservation Organizer, 1997 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 48)
  - Correspondence, 1989-1991 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1993 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 2)
  - Cost Control Measures, 1991 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 3)
  - Council Delegate Report, 1989 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 4)
  - Employee Involvement, Task Force on Process for, 1991 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 5)
  - Executive Committee, Meetings, 1979-1980 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 6)
  - Executive Committee, Meetings, 1981-1983 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 7)
  - Executive Committee, Meetings, 1984-1985 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 8)
  - Executive Committee, Meetings, 1987 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 9)
  - Executive Committee, Meetings, 1988 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 10)
  - Executive Committee, Meetings, 1988 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 11)
  - Executive Committee, Meetings, 1989 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 12)
  - Executive Committee, Meetings, 1991 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 13)
  - Executive Committee, Notes, Undated (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 14)
  - Field Staff, 1990 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 15)
  - Financial Crisis, 1989 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 16)
  - Forms, 1981 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 17)
  - Frost Valley Meetings, 1991 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 18)
  - Fundraising, 1986-1988 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 19)
  - Fundraising, 1989-1990 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 20)
  - Fundraising, 1994-1995 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 21)
  - Gay and Lesbian Sierrans, ca. 1995 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 22)
  - General Records, 1967-1979 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 23)
  - History and Records of the Atlantic Chapter, 1988 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 24)
  - Information Resources, 1993 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 25)
  - Internships, 1984-1995 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 26)
  - Legal Defense Fund, 1974, 1989 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 27)
  - Membership, Address Labels, 1988; Undated (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 28)
  - Membership, Chapter Activity Reports, 1988-1989 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 29)
  - Membership, Chapter Change Report by Chapter for Dues Paid through 9/89, 1989 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 30)
  - Membership, Chapter Change Report by Chapter for Dues Paid through 11/89, 1989 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 31)
  - Membership, Development, 1990-1991; 1993 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 32)
  - Membership, Directories, 1988-1993; Undated (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 33)
  - Membership, Directories, Northeast Conservation Leadership, 1996 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 34)
  - Membership, Directories, State Program Leadership, 1993; 1996 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 35)
  - Membership, Field Recruitment Incentive Program, 1988-1989 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 36)
  - Membership, Field Recruitment Rebate Report for Month of 3/89, 1989 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 37)
  - Membership, Idea Book for Membership Chairs, 1989 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 38)
  - Membership, Leader List by Function, 1988 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 39)
  - Membership, Listing by Regional Group, 1989 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 40)
  - Membership, Listing by Regional Group, 1989 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 41)
  - Membership, Listing by Regional Group, 1989 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 42)
  - Membership, Listing of Entire Chapter, 1989 (Box 3 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 1)
  - Membership, Listing of Entire Chapter, 1989 (Box 3 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 2)
  - Membership, Listing of Entire Chapter, 1989 (Box 3 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 3)
  - Membership, Pocket Cards, Undated (Box 3 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 4)
  - Membership, Questionnaires, 1988 (Box 3 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 5)
  - Memoranda, 1988-1990 (Box 3 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 6)
  - Office Rental, Invoices, 1990 (Box 3 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 7)
  - Personnel, Kath, Shelley, Projects, 1992 (Box 3 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 8)
  - Retreat, 1997 (Box 3 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 9)
  - Senior Advisory Committee, 1987 (Box 3 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 10)
  - Sierra Atlantic, Complimentary Issues Mailing List, 1994 (Box 3 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 11)
  - Staff Organization and Leadership, 1982 (Box 3 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 12)
- Conservation Committees and Regional Groups, 1968-1996; 2; 1.6 cubic ft.
  This series consists of materials by chapter bodies that relate directly to conservation efforts at both the state and regional levels.
  - Conservation Committees, 1983-1993; 2.1; 0.3 cubic ft.
    The conservation committees were part of the statewide organization which focused on a particular environmental issue, such as James Bay or solid waste, that was dealt with statewide. Seven of the eighteen committees listed in the 1993 Chapter Directory (Adirondack, Conservation, Energy, Public Lands, Radioactive Waste, Solid Waste, and Water Resources) are represented here.
    - Conservation Committee, Adirondacks Committee, 1990; 1993 (Box 1 (2-Conservation Committees and Regional ), Folder 1)
    - Conservation Committee, All Chapter Committees, 1986-1989 (Box 1 (2-Conservation Committees and Regional ), Folder 2)
    - Conservation Committee, Conservation Committee, 1986-1990 (Box 1 (2-Conservation Committees and Regional ), Folder 3)
    - Conservation Committee, Conservation Committee, 1986-1990 (Box 1 (2-Conservation Committees and Regional ), Folder 4)
    - Conservation Committee, Contact Persons, Undated (Box 1 (2-Conservation Committees and Regional ), Folder 5)
    - Conservation Committee, Energy Committee, 1983-1988 (Box 1 (2-Conservation Committees and Regional ), Folder 6)
    - Conservation Committee, Energy Committee, 1983-1988 (Box 1 (2-Conservation Committees and Regional ), Folder 7)
    - Conservation Committee, Public Lands Committee, 1987-1988 (Box 1 (2-Conservation Committees and Regional ), Folder 8)
    - Conservation Committee, Radioactive Waste Committee, 1985-1988 (Box 1 (2-Conservation Committees and Regional ), Folder 9)
    - Conservation Committee, Solid Waste Committee, 1987-1988 (Box 1 (2-Conservation Committees and Regional ), Folder 10)
    - Conservation Committee, Water Resources Committees, 1987-1991 (Box 1 (2-Conservation Committees and Regional ), Folder 11)
  - Regional Groups, 1968-1996; 2.2; 1.3 cubic ft.
    The regional groups were the geographic subdivisions of the Atlantic Chapter which handled issues of primarily local interest, for example, contaminated waste sites in particular communities. Items typically found in the regional group records include by-laws, membership information, correspondence, minutes of meetings, financial data, and newsletters. All of the eleven regional groups listed in the 1993 Chapter Directory (Finger Lakes, Hudson-Mohawk, Iroquois, Long Island, Lower Hudson (Westchester/Putnam), Mid-Hudson, New York City, Niagara, Ramapo-Catskill, Rochester, and Susquehanna) are documented here.
    - Regional Groups, All Regional Groups, 1988-1990 (Box 1 (2-Conservation Committees and Regional ), Folder 12)
    - Regional Groups, Blue Sheets, 1994-1995 (Box 1 (2-Conservation Committees and Regional ), Folder 13)
    - Regional Groups, Finger Lakes Group, 1969-1976; 1986-1988 (Box 1 (2-Conservation Committees and Regional ), Folder 14)
    - Regional Groups, Hudson Mohawk Group, Budget, By-laws, Membership, News Clippings, Obeying Schedules, 1979-1994 (Box 1 (2-Conservation Committees and Regional ), Folder 15)
    - Regional Groups, Hudson Mohawk Group, Correspondence, 1979-1994 (Box 1 (2-Conservation Committees and Regional ), Folder 16)
    - Regional Groups, Hudson Mohawk Group, Meetings, 1979-1994 (Box 1 (2-Conservation Committees and Regional ), Folder 17)
    - Regional Groups, Hudson Mohawk Group, Newsletters, 1979-1994 (Box 1 (2-Conservation Committees and Regional ), Folder 18)
    - Regional Groups, Iroquois Group, By-laws, Finances, Membership, News Clippings, Meetings, 1972-1994 (Box 1 (2-Conservation Committees and Regional ), Folder 19)
    - Regional Groups, Iroquois Group, Correspondence, 1972-1994 (Box 1 (2-Conservation Committees and Regional ), Folder 20)